<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-boucadair-connectivity-provisioning-protocol-19"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CPNP">Dynamic Service Negotiation</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." role="editor"
            surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Jacquenet" initials="C." surname="Jacquenet">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>christian.jacquenet@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>dacheng.zhang@huawei.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Panos Georgatsos" initials="P." surname="Georgatsos">
      <organization abbrev="CERTH">Centre for Research and Innovation
      Hellas</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>78, Filikis Etairias str.</street>

          <city>Volos</city>

          <region>Hellas</region>

          <code>38334</code>

          <country>Greece</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+302421306070</phone>

        <email>pgeorgat@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <keyword>SDN, Order Request Handling, Automation, Dynamic Provisioning,
    CDN, Interconnection, Service Delivery, Service Activation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the Connectivity Provisioning Negotiation
      Protocol (CPNP) which is designed to facilitate the dynamic negotiation
      of service parameters.</t>

      <t>CPNP is a generic protocol that can be used for various negotiation
      purposes that include (but are not necessarily limited to) connectivity
      provisioning services, storage facilities, Content Delivery Networks,
      etc.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines the Connectivity Provisioning Negotiation
      Protocol (CPNP) that is meant to dynamically exchange and negotiate
      connectivity provisioning parameters and other service-specific
      parameters between a Customer and a Provider. CPNP is a tool that
      introduces automation in the service negotiation and activation
      procedures, thus fostering the overall service provisioning process.
      CPNP can be seen as a component of the dynamic negotiation meta-domain
      described in Section 3.4 of <xref target="RFC7149"></xref>.</t>

      <t>CPNP is a generic protocol that can be used for other negotiation
      purposes than connectivity provisioning. For example, CPNP can be used
      to request extra storage resources, to extend the footprint of a CDN
      (Content Delivery Networks), to enable additional features from a cloud
      Provider, etc. CPNP can be extended with new Information Elements (IEs).
      Sample negotiation uses cases are described in <xref
      target="suc"></xref>.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC7297"></xref> describes a Connectivity Provisioning
      Profile (CPP) template to capture connectivity requirements to be met by
      a transport infrastructure for the delivery of various services such as
      Voice over IP (VoIP), IPTV, and Virtual Private Network (VPN) services
      <xref target="RFC4026"></xref>. The CPP document defines the set of IP
      transfer parameters that reflect the guarantees that can be provided by
      the underlying transport network together with reachability scope and
      capacity needs. CPNP uses the CPP template to encode connectivity
      provisioning clauses that are subject to negotiation. The agreed CPP
      will be then passed to other functional elements that are responsible
      for the actual service activation and provisioning. For example, NETCONF
      <xref target="RFC6241"></xref> or RESTCONF <xref
      target="RFC8040"></xref> can be used to activate adequate network
      features that are required to deliver the agreed service. How the
      outcome of CPNP negotiation is translated into service and network
      provisioning actions is out of scope of this document.</t>

      <t>As a reminder, several proposals have been made in the past by the
      (research) community (e.g., COPS-SLS <xref
      target="I-D.nguyen-rap-cops-sls"></xref>, Service Negotiation Protocol
      (SrNP) <xref target="TEQUILA"></xref>, Dynamic Service Negotiation
      Protocol (DSNP) <xref target="I-D.itsumo-dsnp"></xref>, Resource
      Negotiation and Pricing Protocol (RNAP) <xref target="Xin"></xref>,
      Service Negotiation and Acquisition Protocol (SNAP) <xref
      target="Karl"></xref>). CPNP leverages the experience of the authors
      with SrNP by separating the negotiation primitives from the service
      under negotiation. Moreover, careful examination of the other proposals
      revealed certain deficiencies that were easier to address through the
      creation of a new protocol rather than modifying existing protocols. For
      example:<list style="symbols">
          <t>COPS-SLS relies upon COPS-PR <xref target="RFC3084"></xref>,
          which is an Historic RFC.</t>

          <t>DSNP is tightly designed with one specific service in mind (QoS)
          and does not make any distinction between a quotation phase and the
          actual service ordering phase.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>One of the primary motivations of this document is to provide a
      permanent reference to exemplify how service negotiation can be
      automated.</t>

      <t>This document is organized as follows:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?><list
          style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="fe"></xref> defines the functional elements
          involved in CPNP exchanges.</t>

          <t><xref target="opm"></xref> introduces several order processing
          models and precises those that are targeted by CPNP.</t>

          <t><xref target="suc"></xref> enumerates a non-exhaustive list of
          use cases that could benefit from CPNP.</t>

          <t><xref target="suc"></xref> discusses CPNP deployment models.</t>

          <t><xref target="cnm"></xref> presents the CPNP negotiation
          model.</t>

          <t><xref target="po"></xref> provides an overview of the
          protocol.</t>

          <t><xref target="co"></xref> specifies the CPNP objects.</t>

          <t><xref target="validation"></xref> describes the CPNP message
          validation procedure.</t>

          <t><xref target="behavior"></xref> specifies the behavior of the
          involved CPNP functional elements.</t>

          <t><xref target="og"></xref> discusses relevant operational
          guidelines.</t>

          <t><xref target="Security"></xref> discusses protocol security
          aspects.<?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Implementation details are out of scope. An example of required
      modules and interfaces to implement this specification is sketched in
      Section 4 of <xref target="AGAVE"></xref>. This specification builds on
      that effort.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document makes use of the following terms:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Customer:">Is a business role which denotes an entity
          that is involved in the definition and the possible negotiation of a
          contract, including a Connectivity Provisioning Agreement, with a
          Provider. A connectivity provisioning contract is captured in a
          dedicated CPP template-based document, which may specify (among
          other information): the sites to be connected, border nodes,
          outsourced operations (e.g., routing, force via points). <vspace
          blankLines="1" />The right to invoke the subscribed service may be
          delegated by the Customer to third-party End Users, or brokering
          services.<vspace blankLines="1" />A Customer can be a Service
          Provider, an application owner, an enterprise, a user, etc.</t>

          <t hangText="Network Provider (or Provider):">Owns and administers
          one or many transport domain(s) (typically Autonomous System (AS))
          composed of (IP) switching and transmission resources (e.g.,
          routing, switching, forwarding, etc.). Network Providers are
          responsible for delivering and operating connectivity services
          (e.g., offering global or restricted reachability at specific
          rates). Offered connectivity services may not necessarily be
          restricted to IP. <vspace blankLines="1" />The policies to be
          enforced by the connectivity service delivery components can be
          derived from the technology-specific clauses that might be included
          in contracts agreed with the Customers. If no such clauses are
          included in the agreement, the mapping between the connectivity
          requirements and the underlying technology-specific policies to be
          enforced is deployment-specific.</t>

          <t hangText="Quotation Order:">Denotes a request made by the
          Customer to the Provider that includes a set of requirements. The
          Customer may express its service-specific requirements by assigning
          (strictly or loosely defined) values to the information items
          included in the commonly understood template (e.g., CPP template)
          describing the offered service. These requirements constitute the
          parameters to be mutually agreed upon.</t>

          <t hangText="Offer:">Refers to a response made by the Provider to a
          Customer's quotation order that describes the ability of the
          Provider to satisfy the order at the time of its receipt. Offers
          reflect the capability of the Provider in accommodating received
          Customer orders beyond monolithic &lsquo;yes/no&rsquo; answers.
          <vspace blankLines="1" />An offer may fully or partially meet the
          requirements of the corresponding order. In the latter case, it may
          include alternative suggestions which the Customer may take into
          account by issuing a new order.</t>

          <t hangText="Agreement:">Refers to an order placed by the Customer
          and accepted by the Provider. It signals the successful conclusion
          of a negotiation cycle.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fe" title="CPNP Functional Elements">
      <t>The following functional elements are defined:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="CPNP client (or client): ">Denotes a software instance
          that sends CPNP requests and receives CPNP responses. The current
          operations that can be performed by a CPNP client are listed
          below:<list style="numbers">
              <t>Create a quotation order (<xref
              target="provision"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Cancel an ongoing quotation order under negotiation (<xref
              target="cancel"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Accept an offer made by a server (<xref
              target="accept"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Withdraw an agreement (<xref target="with"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Update an agreement (<xref target="upd"></xref>).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="CPNP server (or server):">Denotes a software instance
          that receives CPNP requests and sends back CPNP responses
          accordingly. The CPNP server is responsible for the following
          operations:<list style="numbers">
              <t>Process a quotation order (<xref target="proc"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Make an offer (<xref target="offer"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Cancel an ongoing quotation order (<xref
              target="sordu"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Process an order withdrawal (<xref
              target="sordu"></xref>).</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="opm" title="Order Processing Models">
      <t>For preparing their service orders, Customers may need to be aware of
      the offered services. Therefore, Providers should first proceed with the
      announcement (or the exposure) of the services they can provide. The
      service announcement process may take place at designated global or
      Provider-specific service markets, or through explicit interactions with
      the Providers. The details of this process are outside the scope of this
      document.</t>

      <t>With or without such service announcement/exposure mechanisms in
      place, the following order processing models can be distinguished:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Frozen model:"><vspace blankLines="1" />The Customer
          cannot actually negotiate the parameters of the service(s) offered
          by a Provider. After consulting the Provider's service portfolio,
          the Customer selects the service offer he/she wants to subscribe and
          places an order to the Provider. Order handling is quite simple on
          the Provider side because the service is not customized as per
          Customer's requirements, but rather pre-designed to address a
          Customer base that shares the same requirements (i.e., these
          customers share the same Customer Provisioning Profile). This mode
          can be implemented using existing tools such as <xref
          target="RFC8309"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Negotiation-based model:"><vspace
          blankLines="1" />Unlike the frozen model, the Customer documents
          his/her requirements in a request for a quotation, which is then
          sent to one or several Providers. Solicited Providers check whether
          they can address these requirements or not, and get back to the
          Customer accordingly, possibly with an offer that may not exactly
          match customer's requirements (e.g., a 100 Mbps connection cannot be
          provisioned given the amount of available resources, but an 80 Mbps
          connection can be provided). A negotiation between the Customer and
          the Provider(s) then follows until both parties reach an agreement
          (or do not).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Both frozen and negotiation-based models require the existence of
      appropriate service templates like a CPP template and their
      instantiation for expressing specific offerings from Providers and
      service requirements from Customers, respectively. CPNP can be used in
      either model for automating the required Customer-Provider interactions.
      Since the frozen model can be seen as a special case of the
      negotiation-based model, not only &lsquo;yes/no&rsquo; answers but also
      counter-proposals may be offered by the Provider in response to Customer
      orders. This document focuses on the negotiation-based model.</t>

      <t>Order processing management on the Network Provider's side usually
      solicits features supported by the following functional blocks: <?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Network Provisioning (including Order Activation, Network
          Planning, etc.)</t>

          <t>Authentication, Authorization and Accounting (AAA)</t>

          <t>Network and service management (performance measurement and
          assessment, fault detection, etc.)</t>

          <t>Sales-related functional blocks (e.g., billing, invoice
          validation)</t>

          <t>Network Impact Analysis<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>CPNP does not assume any specific knowledge about these functional
      blocks, drawing an explicit line between protocol operation and the
      logic for handling connectivity provisioning requests. An order
      processing logic is typically fed with the information manipulated by
      the aforementioned functional blocks. For example, the resources that
      can be allocated to accommodate Customer's requirements may depend on
      network availability estimates as calculated by the planning functions
      and related policies, as well as the number of orders to be processed
      simultaneously over a given period of time.</t>

      <t>This document does not elaborate on how Customers are identified and
      subsequently managed by the Provider's Information System.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="suc" title="Sample Use Cases ">
      <t>A non-exhaustive list of CPNP use cases is provided below:<list
          style="numbers">
          <t><xref target="RFC4176"></xref> introduces the L3VPN Service Order
          Management functional block which is responsible for managing the
          requests initiated by the Customers and tracks the status of the
          completion of the related operations. CPNP can be used between the
          Customer and the Provider to negotiate L3VPN service parameters.
          <vspace blankLines="1" />A CPNP server could therefore be part of
          the L3VPN Service Order Management functional block discussed in
          <xref target="RFC4176"></xref>. Once an agreement is reached, the
          service can be provisioned using, e.g., <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-l3sm-l3nm"></xref>.</t>

          <t>CPNP can be used between two adjacent domains to deliver IP
          interconnection services (e.g., enable, update, disconnect). For
          example, two Autonomous Systems (ASes) can be connected via several
          interconnection points. CPNP can be used between these ASes to
          upgrade existing links, request additional resources, provision a
          new interconnection point, etc. <vspace blankLines="1" />See, for
          example, the framework documented in <xref
          target="ETICS"></xref>.</t>

          <t>An integrated Provider can use CPNP to rationalize connectivity
          provisioning needs related to its service portfolio. A CPNP server
          function is used by network operations teams. A CPNP interface to
          trigger CPNP negotiation cycles is exposed to service management
          teams.</t>

          <t>Service Providers can use CPNP to initiate connectivity
          provisioning requests towards a number of Network Providers so as to
          optimize the cost of delivering their services. Although multiple
          CPNP ordering cycles can be initiated by a Service Provider towards
          multiple Network Providers, a subset of these orders may actually be
          put into effect.<vspace blankLines="1" />For example, a cloud
          Service Provider can use CPNP to request more resources from Network
          Providers.</t>

          <t>CPNP can also be used in the context of network slicing (<xref
          target="I-D.geng-netslices-architecture"></xref>) to request network
          resources together with a set of requirements that need to be
          satisfied by the Provider. Such requirements are not restricted to
          basic IP forwarding capabilities, but may also include a
          characterization of a set of service functions that may be invoked.
          For the network slicing case, the instances of a CPP template could
          be derived from the network slice templates inputs as documented in
          <xref target="I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi"></xref>.</t>

          <t>CPNP can be used in Machine-to-Machine (M2M) environments to
          dynamically subscribe to M2M services (e.g., access to data
          retrieved by a set of sensors, extend sensor coverage, etc.).<vspace
          blankLines="1" />Also, Internet of Things (IoT, <xref
          target="RFC6574"></xref>) domains may rely on CPNP to enable dynamic
          access to data produced by involved objects, according to their
          specific policies, to various external stakeholders such as data
          analytics and business intelligence companies. Direct CPNP-based
          interactions between IoT domains and interested parties enable open
          access to diverse sets of data across the Internet, e.g., from
          multiple types of sensors, user groups and/or geographical
          areas.</t>

          <t>CPNP can be used in the context of I2NSF (<xref
          target="RFC8329"></xref>) to capture the customer-driven policies to
          be enforced by a set of Network Security Functions.</t>

          <t>A Provider offering cloud services can expose a CPNP interface to
          allow Customers to dynamically negotiate typical data center
          resources, such as additional storage, processing and networking
          resources, enhanced security filters, etc.<vspace
          blankLines="1" />Cloud computing providers typically structure their
          computation service offerings by bundling CPU, RAM, and storage
          units as quotas, instances, or flavors that can be consumed in an
          ephemeral or temporal fashion during the lifetime of the required
          function. A similar approach is followed by CPNP (see for example,
          <xref target="activate"></xref>).</t>

          <t>In the inter-cloud context (also called cloud of clouds or cloud
          federation), CPNP can be used to reserve computing and networking
          resources hosted by various cloud infrastructures.</t>

          <t>CDN Providers can use CPNP to extend their footprint by
          interconnecting their respective CDN infrastructures <xref
          target="RFC6770"></xref> (see <xref target="cdni"></xref>).<vspace
          blankLines="1" /><figure align="center" anchor="cdni"
              title="CDN Interconnection">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[       ,--,--,--.             ,--,--,--.
    ,-'          `-.       ,-'          `-.
   (CDN Provider 'A')=====(CDN Provider 'B')
    `-.  (CDN-A) ,-'       `-. (CDN-B)  ,-'
       `--'--'--'             `--'--'--']]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Mapping Service Providers (MSPs, <xref target="RFC7215"></xref>)
          can use CPNP to enrich their mapping database by interconnecting
          their mapping system (see <xref target="map"></xref>). This
          interconnection allows to relax the constraints on PxTR (Proxy
          Ingress/Egress Tunnel Router) in favour of native LISP (Locator/ID
          Separation Protocol) forwarding <xref target="RFC6830"></xref>.
          Also, it prevents the fragmentation of the LISP mapping database. A
          framework is described in <xref
          target="I-D.boucadair-lisp-idr-ms-discovery"></xref>.<vspace
          blankLines="1" /><figure align="center" anchor="map"
              title="LISP Mapping System Interconnect">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[       ,--,--,--.             ,--,--,--.
    ,-'          `-.       ,-'          `-.
   (Mapping System 'A')===(Mapping System 'B')
    `-.          ,-'       `-.           ,-'
       `--'--'--'             `--'--'--']]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>CPNP may also be used between SDN (Software-Defined Networking)
          controllers in contexts where Cooperating Layered Architecture for
          Software-Defined Networking (CLAS) is enabled <xref
          target="RFC8597"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="dm" title="CPNP Deployment Models">
      <t>Several CPNP deployment models can be envisaged. Two examples are
      listed below:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list style="symbols">
          <t>The Customer deploys a CPNP client while one or several CPNP
          servers are deployed by the Provider. A CPNP client can discover its
          CPNP servers using a variety of means (static, dynamic, etc.).</t>

          <t>The Customer does not enable any CPNP client. The Provider
          maintains a Customer Order Management portal. The Customer can
          initiate connectivity provisioning quotation orders via the portal;
          appropriate CPNP messages are then generated and sent to the
          relevant CPNP server. In this model, both the CPNP client and CPNP
          server are under the responsibility of the same administrative
          entity (i.e., Network Provider).<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Once the negotiation of connectivity provisioning parameters is
      successfully concluded, that is, an order has been placed by the
      Customer, the actual network provisioning operations are initiated. The
      specification of related dynamic resource allocation and policy
      enforcement schemes, as well as how CPNP servers interact with the
      network provisioning functional blocks at Provider sides are out of the
      scope of this document.</t>

      <t>This document does not make any assumption about the CPNP deployment
      model either.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cnm" title="CPNP Negotiation Model">
      <t>CPNP runs between a Customer and a Provider carrying service orders
      from the Customer and corresponding responses from the Provider to the
      end of reaching a service provisioning agreement. As the services
      offered by the Provider are well-described, by means of the CPP template
      for connectivity matters, the negotiation process is essentially a
      value-settlement process, where an agreement is pursued on the values of
      the commonly understood information items (service parameters) included
      in the service description template (<xref
      target="service_template"></xref>).</t>

      <t>The protocol is transparent to the content that it carries and to the
      negotiation logic invoked at Customer and Provider sides, and which
      manipulates the content (i.e., the information carried in CPNP messages
      to proceed with the negotiation).</t>

      <t>The protocol aims at facilitating the execution of the negotiation
      logic by providing the required generic communication primitives.</t>

      <t>Since negotiations are initiated and primarily driven by the
      Customer's negotiation logic, it is reasonable to assume that the
      Customer is the only party that can call for an agreement. An implicit
      approach is adopted for not overloading the protocol with additional
      messages. In particular, the acceptance of an offer made by the Provider
      signals a call for agreement from the Customer. Note that it is almost
      certain the Provider to accept this call since it refers to an offer
      that itself made. Of course, at any point the Provider or the Customer
      may quit the negotiations, each on its own grounds.</t>

      <t>Based on the above, CPNP adopts a Quotation Order/Offer/Answer model,
      which proceeds through the following basic steps (<xref
      target="service_variants"></xref>):</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The CPNP client specifies its service requirements via a
          Provision Quotation Order (PQO). The order may include strictly or
          loosely defined values in the clauses describing service
          provisioning characteristics.</t>

          <t>The CPNP server declines the PQO, or makes an offer to address
          the requirements of the PQO, or suggests a counter-proposal that
          partially addresses the requirements of the PQO in case specific
          requirements cannot be accommodated.</t>

          <t>The CPNP client either accepts or declines the offer. Accepting
          the offer by the CPNP client implies a call for agreement; thus the
          agreement between both parties and the conclusion of the
          negotiation.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="service_variants"
          title="Simplified Service Negotiation">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                     +------+ 
|Client|                     |Server| 
+------+                     +------+ 
   |=====Requested Service=====>|  
   |<=====Offered Service=======|  
   |======Agreed Service=======>| 
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Multiple instances of CPNP may run at Customer's or Provider's
      domains. A CPNP client may be engaged in multiple, simultaneous
      negotiations with the same or different CPNP servers (parallel
      negotiations, see <xref target="mser"></xref>) and a CPNP server may
      need to negotiate with other Provider(s) as part of negotiations that
      are ongoing with a CPNP client (cascaded negotiations, see <xref
      target="cascaded"></xref>).</t>

      <t>CPNP relies on various timers to run its operations. Two types of
      timers are defined: those that are specific to CPNP message transmission
      and those that are specific to the negotiation logic. The latter are
      used to guide the negotiation logic at both CPNP client and CPNP server
      sides, particularly in cases where the CPNP client is involved in
      parallel negotiations with several CPNP servers or in cases where the
      CPNP server is in turn involved in negotiations with other Providers for
      processing a given customer-originated quotation order. CPNP allows a
      CPNP server to request an extra time to proceed with the negotiation.
      This request may be accepted or rejected by the CPNP client.</t>

      <t>Providers may need to publish available services to the Customers
      (see <xref target="opm"></xref>). CPNP may optionally support this
      functionality. Dedicated templates can be defined for the purpose of
      service announcement, which will be used by the CPNP clients to initiate
      their CPNP negotiation cycles.</t>

      <t>For the sake of simplicity, a single Offer/Answer stage is assumed
      within one CPNP negotiation cycle. Nevertheless, as already stated,
      multiple CPNP negotiation cycles can be undertaken by a CPNP client (see
      <xref target="examples"></xref>).</t>

      <t>The model is flexible enough to accommodate changing conditions
      during the lifetime of a service (e.g., introduction of an additional
      VPN site).</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="examples"
          title="Overall Negotiation Process">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                  +------+ +------+                  +------+
|Client|                  |Server| |Client|                  |Server|
+------+                  +------+ +------+                  +------+
   |=====Quotation Order=====>|       |=====Quotation Order=====>|
   |<==========Offer==========|       |<==========Offer==========|
   |===========Accept========>|       |==========Decline========>|

  1-Step Successful Negotiation         1-Step Failed Negotiation
            Cycle                               Cycle

+------+                  +------+ +------+                  +------+
|Client|                  |Server| |Client|                  |Server|
+------+                  +------+ +------+                  +------+
   |===Quotation Order(a)====>|       |===Quotation Order(i)====>|
   |<==========Offer==========|       |<==========Offer==========|   
   |==========Decline========>|       |==========Decline========>|
   |===Quotation Order(b)====>|       |===Quotation Order(j)====>|
   |<==========Offer==========|       |<==========Offer==========|   
   |===========Accept========>|       |==========Decline========>|
                                      |===Quotation Order(k)====>|
                                      |<==========Offer==========| 
                                      |==========Decline========>|
                                      |===Quotation Order(l)====>|
                                      |<==Fail to make an offer==| 

    N-Step Negotiation Cycle:         N-Step Negotiation Cycle:
      Successful Negotiation              Failed Negotiation
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Means used by a CPNP client to retrieve a list of active/agreed
      offers are not defined in this document.</t>

      <t>An order can be implicitly or explicitly activated. Section 3.1 of
      <xref target="RFC7297"></xref> specifies a dedicated clause called
      activation Means. Such clause indicates the required action(s) to be
      undertaken to activate access to the (IP connectivity) service. This
      document defines a dedicated CPNP message that can be used for explicit
      activation (<xref target="activate"></xref>)).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="po" title="Protocol Overview">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Client/Server Communication">
        <t>CPNP is a client/server protocol that can run over any transport
        protocol. Yet, UDP is the default transport mode secured with Datagram
        Transport Layer Security (DTLS) <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>. No
        permanent CPNP transport session needs to be maintained between the
        client and the server.</t>

        <t>The CPNP client can be configured with the CPNP server(s).
        Typically, an IP address together with a port number are configured to
        the CPNP client, based upon manual or dynamic configuration means
        (e.g., DHCP). Alternatively, a Provider may advertise the port number
        (CPNP_PORT) it uses to bind the CPNP service using SRV <xref
        target="RFC2782"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The client sends CPNP requests using CPNP_PORT as the destination
        port number. The same port number used as the source port number of a
        CPNP request sent to a CPNP server is used by the server to reply to
        that request.</t>

        <t>CPNP is independent of the IP address family.</t>

        <t>CPNP retransmission is discussed in <xref target="retrans"></xref>
        for unreliable transports.</t>

        <t>Considerations related to mutual authentication are discussed in
        <xref target="Security"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Policy Configuration on the CPNP Server">
        <t>As an input to its decision-making process, the CPNP server may be
        connected to various external modules such as: Customer Profiles,
        Network Topology, Network Resource Management, Order Repositories, AAA
        and Network Provisioning Manager (an example is shown in <xref
        target="fb"></xref>).</t>

        <t>These external modules provide inputs to the CPNP server, so that
        it can:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Check whether a customer is entitled to initiate a provisioning
            quotation request.</t>

            <t>Check whether a customer is entitled to cancel an ongoing
            order.</t>

            <t>Check whether administrative data (e.g., billing-related
            information) have been verified before the processing of the
            request starts.</t>

            <t>Check whether network capacity is available or additional
            capacity is required.</t>

            <t>Receive guidelines from network design and sales blocks (e.g.,
            pricing, network usage levels, thresholds associated with the
            number of CPP templates that can be processed over a given period
            of time as a function of the nature of the service to be
            delivered, etc.).</t>

            <t>Transfer completed orders to network provisioning blocks. For
            example, the outcome of CPNP may be passed to modules such as
            Application-Based Network Operations (ABNO) <xref
            target="RFC7491"></xref> or network controllers. These controllers
            will use protocols such as NETCONF <xref target="RFC6241"></xref>
            to interact with the appropriate network nodes and functions for
            the sake of proper service activation and delivery. <?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
          </list>The above list of CPNP server operations is not
        exhaustive.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="fb"
            title="Order Handling Management Functional Block (Focus on Internal Interfaces)">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[       . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
       .Business & Administrative Management                   .      
       .+------------------------++---------------------------+.  
       .| Business Guidelines    ||    Billing & Charging     |.
       .+-----------+------------++-----------+---------------+.
       .            |                         |                .
       .            +-------------------+     |                .
       . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .|. . .|. . . . . . . . .
       . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .|. . .|. . . . . . . . .
       .Order Handling Management       |     |                .
       . +-------------------+  +-------+-----+--------------+ .
       . |Network Topology DB+--+        CPNP Server         | .
       . +-------------------+  +-+---+---+---+---+-----+----+ . 
       .                          |   |   |   |   |     |      .
       . +------------------------+-+ |   |   |   |     |      .
       . |   Network Dimensioning   | |   |   |   |     |      .
       . |        & Planning        | |   |   |   |     |      .
       . +--------------------------+ |   |   |   |     |      .
       . +----------------------------+-+ |   |   | +---+----+ .
       . |                              | |   |   | |   AAA  | .
       . |   Network       +------------+ |   |   | +--------+ .
       . |  Resource       | +------------+-+ | +-+----------+ .
       . |  Management     | |   Customer   | | |   Orders   | .
       . |                 | |   Profiles   | | | Repository | .
       . +-----------------+ +--------------+ | +------------+ .
       . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .|. . . . . . . . .
       +--------------------------------------+----------------+
       |             Network Provisioning Manager              |   
       +-------------------------------------------------------+   
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>

        <t>The following order handling modes can also be configured on the
        server:<list style="numbers">
            <t>Fully automated mode: This mode does not require any action
            from the administrator when receiving a request for a service. The
            server can execute its decision-making process related to the
            orders received and generate corresponding offers.</t>

            <t>Administrative validation checking: Some or all of the server's
            operations are subject to administrative validation procedures.
            This mode requires an action from the administrator for every
            request received. To that aim, the CPNP methods which can be
            automatically handled by the server (or are subject to one or
            several validation administrative checks) can be configured on the
            server.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="session" title="CPNP Session Entries">
        <t>A CPNP session entry is denoted by a tuplet defined as
        follows:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Transport session (typically, IP address of the CPNP client,
            client's port number, IP address of the CPNP server, and CPNP
            server's port number).</t>

            <t>Incremented Sequence Number (<xref target="sq_nu"></xref>)</t>

            <t>Customer Agreement Identifier: This is a unique identifier
            assigned to the order under negotiation by the CPNP client (<xref
            target="cu_id"></xref>). This identifier is also used to identify
            the agreement that will result from a successful negotiation.</t>

            <t>Provider Agreement Identifier: This is a unique identifier
            assigned to the order under negotiation by the CPNP server (<xref
            target="pr_id"></xref>). This identifier is also used to identify
            the agreement that will result from a successful negotiation.</t>

            <t>Transaction-ID (<xref target="trans"></xref>).</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trans" title="CPNP Transaction">
        <t>A CPNP transaction occurs between a client and a server for
        completing, modifying, withdrawing a service agreement, and comprises
        all CPNP messages exchanged between the client and the server, from
        the first request sent by the client to the final response sent by the
        server. A CPNP transaction is bound to a CPNP session (<xref
        target="session"></xref>).</t>

        <t>Because multiple CPNP transactions can be maintained by the CPNP
        client, the client must assign an identifier to uniquely identify a
        given transaction. This identifier is denoted as Transaction-ID.</t>

        <t>The Transaction-ID must be randomly assigned by the CPNP client,
        according to the best current practice for generating random numbers
        <xref target="RFC4086"></xref> that cannot be guessed easily.
        Transaction-ID is used for validating CPNP responses received by the
        client.</t>

        <t>In the context of a transaction, the client needs to randomly
        select a sequence number and assign it to the first CPNP message to
        send. This number is then incremented for each request message that is
        subsequently sent within the ongoing CPNP transaction (see <xref
        target="sq_nu"></xref>).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="timers" title="CPNP Timers">
        <t>CPNP adopts a simple retransmission procedure which relies on a
        retransmission timer denoted as RETRANS_TIMER and a maximum retry
        threshold. The use of RETRANS_TIMER and a maximum retry threshold are
        described in <xref target="behavior"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The response timer (EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME) is set by the client to
        denote the time, in seconds, the client will wait for receiving a
        response from the server to a provisioning quotation order request
        (see <xref target="extime"></xref>). If the timer expires, the
        respective quotation order is cancelled by the client and a CANCEL
        message is generated accordingly.</t>

        <t>The expected offer timer (EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME) is set by the server
        to indicate the time by when the CPNP server is expecting to make an
        offer to the CPNP client (see <xref
        target="EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME"></xref>). If no offer is received by
        then, the CPNP client will consider the order as rejected.</t>

        <t>An offer expiration timer (VALIDITY_OFFER_TIME) is set by the
        server to represent the time, in minutes, after which an offer made by
        the server becomes invalid (see <xref target="valtime"></xref>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="CPNP Operations">
        <t>CPNP operations are listed below. They may be augmented, depending
        on the nature of some transactions or because of security
        considerations that may necessitate a distinct CPNP client/server
        authentication phase before negotiation begins. <list style="symbols">
            <t>QUOTATION (<xref target="provision"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the client to initiate
            a provisioning quotation order. Upon receipt of a QUOTATION
            request, the server may respond with a PROCESSING, OFFER or a FAIL
            message. A QUOTATION-initiated transaction can be terminated by a
            FAIL message.</t>

            <t>PROCESSING (<xref target="proc"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used to inform the remote party
            that the message (the order quotation or the offer) sent was
            received and it is processed. This message can also be issued by
            the server to request more time, in which case the client may
            reply with an ACK or FAIL message depending on whether extra time
            can or cannot be granted.</t>

            <t>OFFER (<xref target="offer"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the server to inform
            the client about an offer that can best accommodate the
            requirements indicated in the previously received QUOTATION
            message.</t>

            <t>ACCEPT (<xref target="accept"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the client to confirm
            the acceptance of an offer made by the server. This message
            implies a call for agreement. An agreement is reached when an ACK
            is subsequently received from the server, which is likely to
            happen if the message is sent before the offer validity time
            expires; the server is unlikely to reject an offer that it has
            already made.</t>

            <t>DECLINE (<xref target="dec"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the client to reject an
            offer made by the server. The ongoing transaction may not be
            terminated immediately, e.g., the server/client may issue another
            offer/order.</t>

            <t>ACK (<xref target="ack"></xref>): <vspace blankLines="1" />This
            operation is used by the server to acknowledge the receipt of an
            ACCEPT or WITHDRAW message, or by the client to confirm the time
            extension requested (conveyed in a PROCESSING message) by the
            server for processing the last received quotation order.</t>

            <t>CANCEL (<xref target="cancel"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the client to cancel
            (quit) the ongoing transaction.</t>

            <t>WITHDRAW (<xref target="with"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the client to withdraw
            an agreement.</t>

            <t>UPDATE (<xref target="upd"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the client to update an
            existing agreement. For example, this method can be invoked to add
            a new VPN site. This method will trigger a new negotiation
            cycle.</t>

            <t>FAIL (<xref target="fail"></xref>): <vspace
            blankLines="1" />This operation is used by the server to indicate
            that it cannot accommodate the requirements documented in the PQO
            conveyed in the QUOTATION message or to inform the client about an
            error encountered when processing the received message. In either
            case, the message implies that the server is unable to make offers
            and as a consequence, it terminates the ongoing transaction.
            <vspace blankLines="1" />This message is also used by the client
            to reject a time extension request received from the server (in a
            PROCESSING message). The message includes a status code for
            providing explanatory information.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The above CPNP primitives are service-independent. CPNP messages
        may transparently carry service-specific objects which are handled by
        the negotiation logic at either side.</t>

        <t>The document specifies the service objects that are required for
        connectivity provisioning negotiation (see <xref target="cpd"></xref>)
        purposes. Additional service-specific objects to be carried in CPNP
        messages can be defined in the future for accommodating alternative
        deployment schemes or other service provisioning needs.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cpd" title="Connectivity Provisioning Documents">
        <t>CPNP makes use of several flavors of Connectivity Provisioning
        Documents (CPD). These documents follow the same CPP template
        described in <xref target="RFC7297"></xref>.<list style="hanging">
            <t
            hangText="Requested Connectivity Provisioning Document (Requested CPD): ">Refers
            to the CPD included by a CPNP client in a QUOTATION request.</t>

            <t
            hangText="Offered Connectivity Provisioning Document (Offered CPD): ">This
            document is included by a CPNP server in an OFFER message. Its
            information reflects the proposal of the server to accommodate all
            or a subset of the clauses depicted in a Requested CPD. A validity
            time is associated with the offer made.</t>

            <t
            hangText="Agreed Connectivity Provisioning Document (Agreed CPD): ">If
            the client accepts an offer made by the server, the Offered CPD is
            included in an ACCEPT message. This CPD is also included in an ACK
            message. Thus, a 3-way handshake procedure is followed for
            successfully completing the negotiation.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><xref target="example"></xref> shows a typical CPNP negotiation
        cycle and the use of the different types of Connectivity Provisioning
        Documents.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="example"
            title="Connectivity Provisioning Documents">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |======QUOTATION (Requested CPD)=====>|
   |<============PROCESSING==============|
   |<========OFFER (Offered CPD)=========|
   |=============PROCESSING=============>|
   |=========ACCEPT (Agreed CPD)========>|
   |<=========ACK (Agreed CPD)===========|
   |                                     |
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>A provisioning document can include parameters with fixed values,
        loosely-defined values, or any combination thereof. A provisioning
        document is said to be concrete if all clauses have fixed values.</t>

        <t>A typical evolution of a negotiation cycle would start with a
        quotation order with loosely-defined parameters, and then, as offers
        are made, it would conclude with concrete provisioning document for
        calling for the agreement.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cascaded" title="Child Provisioning Quotation Orders">
        <t>If the server detects that network resources from another Network
        Provider need to be allocated in order to accommodate the requirements
        described in a PQO (e.g., in the context of an inter-domain VPN
        service, additional PE router resources need to be allocated), the
        server may generate child PQOs to request the appropriate network
        provisioning operations (see <xref target="child"></xref>). In such
        situation, the server behaves also as a CPNP client. The server
        associates the parent order with its child PQOs. How this is achieved
        is implementation-specific (e.g., this can be typically achieved by
        locally adding the reference of the child PQO to the parent
        order).</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="child"
            title="Example of Child Orders">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+            +--------+          +--------+
|Client|            |Server A|          |Server B|
+------+            +--------+          +--------+
   |                    |                    |
   |=====QUOTATION=====>|                    |
   |<====PROCESSING=====|                    |
   |                    |=====QUOTATION=====>|
   |                    |<====PROCESSING=====|
   |                    |<=======OFFER=======|
   |                    |=====PROCESSING====>|
   |                    |=======ACCEPT======>|
   |                    |<=======ACK=========|
   |<=======OFFER=======|                    |
   |=====PROCESSING====>|                    |
   |=======ACCEPT======>|                    |
   |<=======ACK=========|                    |
   |                    |                    |
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multi-Segment Service">
        <t>A composite service (e.g., connectivity) requested by a customer
        could imply multi-segment services (e.g., multi-segment connectivity
        spanning an end-to-end scope), in the sense that one single CPNP
        request is decomposed into N connectivity requests at the provider's
        side (thereby leading to child orders). The Provider is in charge of
        handling the complexity of splitting the generic provisioning order in
        a multi-segment context. Such complexity is local to the Provider.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="mser" title="Negotiating with Multiple CPNP Servers">
        <t>A CPNP client may undertake multiple negotiations in parallel with
        several servers for various reasons, such as cost optimization and
        fail-safety. These multiple negotiations may lead to one or many
        agreements.</t>

        <t>The salient point underlining the parallel negotiation scenarios is
        that, although the negotiation protocol is strictly between two
        parties, this may not be the case of the negotiation logic. The CPNP
        client negotiation logic may need to collectively drive parallel
        negotiations, as the negotiation with one server may affect the
        negotiation with other servers; for example, it may need to use the
        responses from all servers as an input for determining the messages
        (and their content) to subsequently send within the course of each
        individual negotiation. Timing is therefore an important aspect at the
        client's side. The CPNP client needs to have the ability to
        synchronize the receipt of the responses from the servers. CPNP takes
        into account this requirement by allowing clients to specify in the
        QUOTATION message the time by which the server needs to respond (see
        <xref target="extime"></xref>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="State Management">
        <t>Both the client and the server maintain repositories to store
        ongoing orders. How these repositories are maintained is
        deployment-specific. It is out of scope of this document to elaborate
        on such considerations. Timestamps are also logged to track state
        change. Tracking may be needed for various reasons, including
        regulatory or billing ones.</t>

        <t>In order to accommodate failures that may lead to the reboot of the
        client or the server, the use of permanent storage is recommended,
        thereby facilitating state recovery. <!--
--></t>

        <section title="On the Client Side">
          <t>This is the list of the typical states that can be associated
          with a given order on the client's side:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Created: when the order has been created. It is not handled
              by the client until the administrator allows to process it.</t>

              <t>AwaitingProcessing: when the administrator approved the
              processing of a created order and the order has not been handled
              yet.</t>

              <t>PQOSent: when the order has been sent to the server.</t>

              <t>ServerProcessing: when the server has confirmed the receipt
              of the order.</t>

              <t>OfferReceived: when an offer has been received from the
              server.</t>

              <t>OfferProcessing: when a received offer is currently processed
              by the client.</t>

              <t>AcceptSent: when the client confirmed the offer to the
              server.</t>

              <t>Completed: when the offer is acknowledged by the server.</t>

              <t>Cancelled: when the order has failed or cancelled.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Sub-states may be defined (e.g., to track failed vs. cancelled
          orders) but those are not shown in <xref
          target="clientstate"></xref>.</t>

          <t><figure align="center" anchor="clientstate"
              title="Example of a CPNP Finite State Machine (Client Side)">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------------------+
|     Created      |-----------------+
+------------------+                 |
        |                            |
        v                            |
+------------------+                 |
|AwaitingProcessing|----------------+|
+------------------+                || 
        |                           ||
   QUOTATION/UPDATE                 ||
        v                           ||
+------------------+                ||
|     PQOSent      |---CANCEL------+||
+------------------+               vvv
        |                        +-----+
    PROCESSING                   |     |
        v                        |     |
+------------------+   CANCEL    |  C  |
| ServerProcessing |------------>|  A  |
+------------------+    FAIL     |  N  |
        |                        |  C  |
        |                        |  E  | 
      OFFER                      |  L  |
        |                        |  L  |
        v                        |  E  |
+------------------+             |  D  |
|  OfferReceived   |---CANCEL--->|     |
+------------------+             |     |
        | PROCESSING             +-----+
        v                          ^^^
+------------------+               |||
|  OfferProcessing |---DECLINE-----+||
+------------------+                ||
        | ACCEPT                    ||
        v                           ||
+------------------+                ||
|    AcceptSent    |---CANCEL-------+|
+------------------+                 |
        | ACK                        |
        v                            |
+------------------+                 |
|   Completed      |---WITHDRAW------+
+------------------+
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section title="On the Server Side">
          <t>The following lists the states which can be associated with a
          given order and a corresponding offer on the server's side:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>PQOReceived: when the order has been received from the
              client.</t>

              <t>AwaitingProcessing: when the order is being processed by the
              server. An action from the server administrator may be
              needed.</t>

              <t>OfferProposed: when the request has been successfully handled
              and an offer has been sent to the client.</t>

              <t>ProcessingReceived: when the server received a PROCESSING for
              an offer sent to the client.</t>

              <t>AcceptReceived: when the server received a confirmation for
              the offer from the client.</t>

              <t>Completed: when the server acknowledged the offer (accepted
              by client) to the client. Transitioning to this state assumes
              that the ACK was received by the client (this can be detected by
              the server if it receives retransmitted ACCEPT from the
              client).</t>

              <t>Cancelled: when the order cannot be accommodated or it has
              been cancelled by the client. Associate resources must be
              released in the latter case, if previously reserved.</t>

              <t>ChildCreated: when a child order has been created in cases
              where resources from another Network Provider are needed.</t>

              <t>ChildPQOSent: when a child order has been sent to the remote
              server.</t>

              <t>ChildServerProcessing: when a child order is currently
              processed by the remote server.</t>

              <t>ChildOfferReceived: when an offer has been received to a
              child order from the remote server.</t>

              <t>ChildOfferProcessing: when a received offer to a child order
              is currently processed.</t>

              <t>ChildAcceptSent: when the child offer (offer received from
              the remote server in response to a child order) is confirmed to
              the remote server.</t>

              <t>ChildCompleted: when an accepted child offer is acknowledged
              by the remote server.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><figure align="center" anchor="serverstate"
              title="CPNP Finite State Machine (Server Side)">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------------------+           +------------------+    
|AwaitingProcessing|<----------|    ChildCreated  |                        
+------------------+           +------------------+                   
        |                            |      ^ 
        v                            |      |                                                
+------------------+                 |      |           
|   ChildPQOSent   |----------------+|      Q     
+------------------+                ||      U              
        |                           ||      O                 
     QUOTATION/UPDATE               ||      T                  
        v                           ||      A  +--------------------+ 
+---------------------+   CANCEL    ||      T  |     PQOReceived    |      
|ChildServerProcessing|------------+||      I  +--------------------+ 
+---------------------+    FAIL    vvv      O       |      |  
        |                        +-----+    N    CANCEL    |
    PROCESSING                   |     |<---|-------+  PROCESSING
        v                        |     |    |              v
+------------------+             |     |   +------------------------+            
|ChildOfferReceived|----CANCEL---|  C  |<--|   AwaitingProcessing   |  
+------------------+             |  A  |   +------------------------+ 
        |                        |  N  |       ^          | OFFER
      OFFER                      |  C  |       | +------------------+ 
        |                        |  E  |<DECLINE-|   OfferProposed  |
        |                        |  L  |       | +------------------+     
        v                        |  L  |       |          |
+------------------+             |  E  |       |      PROCESSING
|ChildOfferReceived|---CANCEL----|  D  |       |          v
+------------------+             |     |       | +------------------+      
        |                        |     |<DECLINE-| Proc'ingReceived |     
   PROCESSING                    |     |       |+------------------+       
        |                        +-----+       |          | ACCEPT
        v                         ^^^^^        |          v  
+------------------+              |||||        | +------------------+
|ChildOfferProc'ing|---DECLINE----+|||+-CANCEL-|-|  AcceptReceived  |       
+------------------+               |||         | +------------------+ 
        |ACCEPT                    |||         |          |ACK
        v                          |||         |          v   
+------------------+               |||         | +------------------+
|  ChildAcceptSent |---CANCEL------+|+-WITHDRAW|-|    Completed     |       
+------------------+                |          | +------------------+                  
        | ACK                       |          |
        v                           |          |
+------------------+                |          |
|  ChildCompleted  |---WITHDRAW-----+          |
|                  +---------------------------+
+------------------+
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="co" title="CPNP Objects">
      <t>This section defines CPNP objects using the RBNF format defined at
      <xref target="RFC5511"></xref>.</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Note 1: The formats of CPNP messages are provided using a generic
          format. Implementors can adapt RBNF definitions to their "favorite"
          message format. For example, JSON <xref target="RFC8259"></xref> or
          CBOR <xref target="RFC7049"></xref> can be used.</t>

          <t>Note 2: CPNP messages cannot be blindly mapped to RESTCONF
          messages with the target service being modelled as configuration
          data because such data is supposed to be manipulated by a RESTCONF
          client only. In such model, the RESTCONF server cannot use a value
          other than the one set by the client (e.g., <xref
          target="offer"></xref>) or remove offers from its own initiative
          (e.g., <xref target="valtime"></xref>). An alternate approach might
          be to map CPNP operations into RESTCONF actions (rpc). Assessing the
          feasibility of such approach is out of scope.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

      <section title="Attributes">
        <t></t>

        <section anchor="cu_id" title="CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER">
          <t>CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER is an identifier which is assigned
          by a client to identify an agreement. This identifier must be unique
          to the client.</t>

          <t>Rules for assigning this identifier are specific to the client
          (Customer). The value of CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER is included
          in all CPNP messages.</t>

          <t>The client (Customer) assigns an identifier to an order under
          negotiation before an agreement is reached. This identifier will be
          used to unambiguously identify the resulting agreement at the client
          side (Customer).</t>

          <t>The server handles CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER as an opaque
          value.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="pr_id" title="PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER">
          <t>PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER is an identifier which is assigned
          by a server to identify an order. This identifier must be unique to
          the server.</t>

          <t>Rules for assigning this identifier are specific to the server
          (Provider). PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER is included in all CPNP
          messages, except QUOTATION messages (because the state is only
          present at the client side).</t>

          <t>The server (Provider) assigns an identifier to an order under
          negotiation before an agreement is reached. This identifier will be
          used to unambiguously identify the resulting agreement at the server
          side (Provider).</t>

          <t>The client handles PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER as an opaque
          value.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="trans_id" title="TRANSACTION_ID">
          <t>This object conveys the Transaction-ID introduced in <xref
          target="trans"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="SEQUENCE_NUMBER">
          <t>Sequence Number is a number that is monotonically incremented in
          every new CPNP message pertaining to a given CPNP transaction. This
          number is used to avoid reply attacks.</t>

          <t>Refer to <xref target="sq_nu"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="NONCE">
          <t>NONCE is a random value assigned by the CPNP server. It is
          RECOMMENDED to assign unique NONCE values for each order.</t>

          <t>NONCE is then mandatory to be included in subsequent CPNP client
          operations on the associated order (including the resulting
          agreement) such as: withdraw the order or update the order.</t>

          <t>If the NONCE validation checks fail, the server rejects the
          request with a FAIL message including the appropriate failure reason
          code.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="extime" title="EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME">
          <t>This attribute indicates the time by when the CPNP client is
          expecting to receive a response from the CPNP server to a given PQO.
          If no offer is received by then, the CPNP client will consider the
          quotation order as rejected.</t>

          <t>EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME follows the date format specified in <xref
          target="RFC3339"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME" title="EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME">
          <t>This attribute indicates the time by when the CPNP server is
          expecting to make an offer to the CPNP client. If no offer is
          received by then, the CPNP client will consider the order as
          rejected.</t>

          <t>The CPNP server may propose an expected offer time that does not
          match the expected response time indicated in the quotation order
          message. The CPNP client can accept or reject the proposed expected
          time by when the CPNP server will make an offer.</t>

          <t>The CPNP server can always request extra time for its processing,
          but this may be accepted or rejected by the CPNP client.</t>

          <t>EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME follows the date format specified in <xref
          target="RFC3339"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="valtime" title="VALIDITY_OFFER_TIME">
          <t>This attribute indicates the time of validity of an offer made by
          the CPNP server. If the offer is not accepted before this date
          expires, the CPNP server will consider the CPNP client has rejected
          the offer; the CPNP server will silently remove this order from its
          base.</t>

          <t>VALIDITY_OFFER_TIME follows date format specified in <xref
          target="RFC3339"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="service_template" title="SERVICE_DESCRIPTION">
          <t>This document specifies a machinery to negotiate any aspect
          subject to negotiation. Service clauses that are under negotiation
          are conveyed using this attribute.</t>

          <t>The structure of the connectivity provisioning clauses is
          provided in the following sub-section.</t>

          <section anchor="cpd_template"
                   title="CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT">
            <t>The RBNF format of the Connectivity Provisioning Document (CPD)
            is shown in <xref target="rbnf_cpd"></xref>:</t>

            <t><figure anchor="rbnf_cpd"
                title="The RBNF format of the Connectivity Provisioning Document (CPD)">
                <artwork><![CDATA[<CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT> ::= 
                           <Connectivity Provisioning Component> ...
<Connectivity Provisioning Component> ::= 
                           <CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_PROFILE> ...
<CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_PROFILE> ::= 
                           <Customer Nodes Map>
                           <SCOPE>
                           <QoS Guarantees>
                           <Availability>
                           <CAPACITY>
                           <Traffic Isolation>
                           <Conformance Traffic>
                           <Flow Identification>
                           <Overall Traffic Guarantees>
                           <Routing and Forwarding>
                           <Activation Means>
                           <Invocation Means>
                           <Notifications>
<Customer Nodes Map> ::=  <Customer Node> ...
<Customer Node> ::=  <IDENTIFIER>
                     <LINK_IDENTIFIER>
                     <LOCALISATION>]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="CPNP Information Elements">
          <t>An Information Element (IE) is an optional object which can be
          included in a CPNP message.</t>

          <section title="Customer Description">
            <t>The client may include administrative information such
            as:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list style="symbols">
                <t>Name</t>

                <t>Contact Information<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
              </list>The format of this Information Element is as follows:</t>

            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[<Customer Description> ::= [<NAME>] [<Contact Information>]
<Contact Information> ::=  [<EMAIL_ADDRESS>] [<POSTAL_ADDRESS>]
                           [<TELEPHONE_NUMBER> ...]
]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Provider Description">
            <t>The server may include administrative information in an offer
            such as:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list style="symbols">
                <t>Name</t>

                <t>AS Number (<xref target="RFC6793"></xref>)</t>

                <t>Contact Information<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
              </list>The format of this Information Element is as follows:</t>

            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[<Provider Description> ::= [<NAME>][<Contact Information>][<AS_NUMBER>]
]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Negotiation Options">
            <t>The client may include some negotiation options such as:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list
                style="symbols">
                <t>Setup purpose: A client may request the setup of a service
                (e.g., connectivity) only for testing purposes during a
                limited period. The order can be extended to become permanent
                if the client was satisfied during the test period. This
                operation is achieved using the UPDATE method.</t>

                <t>Activation type: A client may request a permanent or
                scheduled activation type. If no activation type clause is
                included during the negotiation, this means that the order
                will be immediately activated right after the negotiation
                ends.<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The format of this Information Element is as follows:</t>

            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[<Negotiation Options> ::= [<PURPOSE>]
]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Operation Messages">
        <t>This section specifies the RBNF format of CPNP operation messages.
        The following operation codes are used: <?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

        <t><list style="format %d:">
            <t>QUOTATION (<xref target="provision"></xref>)</t>

            <t>PROCESSING (<xref target="proc"></xref>)</t>

            <t>OFFER (<xref target="offer"></xref>)</t>

            <t>ACCEPT (<xref target="accept"></xref>)</t>

            <t>DECLINE (<xref target="dec"></xref>)</t>

            <t>ACK (<xref target="ack"></xref>)</t>

            <t>CANCEL (<xref target="cancel"></xref>)</t>

            <t>WITHDRAW (<xref target="with"></xref>)</t>

            <t>UPDATE (<xref target="upd"></xref>)</t>

            <t>FAIL (<xref target="fail"></xref>)</t>

            <t>ACTIVATE (<xref target="activate"></xref>)<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>These codes are used to unambiguously identify a CPNP operation;
        the operation code is conveyed in the "METHOD_CODE" attribute
        mentioned in the following sub-sections.</t>

        <t>In the following, "VERSION" refers to the CPNP version number. This
        attribute MUST be set to 1.</t>

        <section anchor="provision" title="QUOTATION">
          <t>The format of the QUOTATION message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="23" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;QUOTATION Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME&gt;]</t>

              <t>&lt;REQUESTED_CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>A QUOTATION message MUST include an order
          identifier which is generated by the client
          (CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER). Because several orders can be
          issued to several servers, the QUOTATION message MUST also include a
          Transaction-ID.</t>

          <t>The message MAY include an EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME which indicates
          by when the client is expecting to receive an offer from the server.
          QUOTATION message MUST also include a requested service description
          (that is, requested connectivity provisioning document for
          connectivity services).</t>

          <t>The message MAY include ACTIVATION_TYPE to request a permanent or
          scheduled activation type (e.g., using the ACTIVATE method defined
          in <xref target="activate"></xref>). If no such clause is included,
          the default mode is to assume that the order will be active once the
          agreed activation means are successfully invoked (e.g., Section 3.11
          of <xref target="RFC7297"></xref>).</t>

          <t>When the client sends the QUOTATION message to the server, the
          state of the order changes to "PQOSent" at the client side.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="proc" title="PROCESSING">
          <t>The format of the PROCESSING message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="25" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;PROCESSING Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME&gt;]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>Upon receipt of a QUOTATION message, the
          server proceeds with parsing rules (see <xref
          target="validation"></xref>). If no error is encountered, the server
          generates a PROCESSING response to the client to indicate the PQO
          has been received and it is being processed. The server MUST
          generate an order identifier which identifies the order in its local
          order repository. The server MUST copy the content of
          CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER and TRANSACTION_ID fields as conveyed
          in the QUOTATION message. The server MAY include an
          EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME by when it expects to make an offer to the
          client.</t>

          <t>Upon receipt of a PROCESSING message, the client verifies whether
          it has issued a PQO to that server and which contains the
          CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER and TRANSACTION_ID. If no such PQO is
          found, the PROCESSING message MUST be silently ignored. If a PQO is
          found, the client may check whether it accepts the
          EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME and then, it changes to state of the order to
          "ServerProcessing".</t>

          <t>If more time is required by the server to process the quotation
          order, it MAY send a PROCESSING message that includes a new
          EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME. The client can answer with an ACK message if
          more time is granted (<xref target="timegranted"></xref>) or with a
          FAIL message if the time extension request is rejected (<xref
          target="timerejected"></xref>).</t>

          <t><figure align="center" anchor="timegranted"
              title="Request More Negotiation Time: Granted">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |=======QUOTATION(Requested CPD)=====>|
   |<========PROCESSING(time1)===========|
                     ...
   |<========PROCESSING(MoreTime)========|
   |============ACK(TimeGranted)========>|
                     ...
   |<=========OFFER(Offered CPD)=========|
   |=============PROCESSING=============>|
   |==========ACCEPT(Agreed CPD)========>|
   |<==========ACK(Agreed CPD)===========|
   |                                     |
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t><figure align="center" anchor="timerejected"
              title="Request More Negotiation Time: Rejected">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |=======QUOTATION(Requested CPD)=====>|
   |<========PROCESSING(time1)===========|
                     ...
   |<========PROCESSING(MoreTime)========|
   |=====FAIL(More Time Rejected)=======>|
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="offer" title="OFFER">
          <t>The format of the OFFER message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="20" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;OFFER Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;NONCE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;VALIDITY_OFFER_TIME&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;OFFERED_CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>The server answers with an OFFER message
          to a QUOTATION request received from the client. The offer will be
          considered as rejected by the client if no confirmation (ACCEPT
          message sent by the client) is received by the server before the
          expiration of the validity time.</t>

          <t>The server MAY include ACTIVATION_TYPE to indicate whether the
          offer is about a permanent or scheduled activation type. The message
          MAY include ACTIVATION_SCHEDULE to indicate when the order is to be
          activated. If no such clause is included, the default mode is to
          assume that the order will be active once the agreed activation
          means are successfully invoked (e.g., Section 3.11 of <xref
          target="RFC7297"></xref> or <xref target="activate"></xref>).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="accept" title="ACCEPT">
          <t>The format of the ACCEPT message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="22" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;ACCEPT Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;NONCE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;AGREED_CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This message is used by a client to
          confirm the acceptance of an offer received from a server. The
          fields of this message MUST be copied from the received OFFER
          message. This message SHOULD NOT be sent after the validity time of
          the offer expires, as indicated by the server (<xref
          target="offer"></xref>).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dec" title="DECLINE">
          <t>The format of the DECLINE message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="21" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;DECLINE Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;NONCE&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;REASON&gt;...]</t>
            </list><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>The client may issue a DECLINE
          message to reject an offer. CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER,
          PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, TRANSACTION_ID, and NONCE are used by
          the server as keys to find the corresponding order. If an order
          matches, the server changes the state of this order to "Cancelled"
          and then returns an ACK with a copy of the requested CPD to the
          requesting client.</t>

          <t>A DECLINE message MAY include an information to indicate the
          reason for declining an offer. The following codes are defined:
          <list style="empty">
              <t>1 (Unacceptable gap between the request and the offer)</t>

              <t>2 (Conflict with another offer from another server)</t>

              <t>3 (Activation type mismatch)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>If no order is found, the server returns a FAIL message to the
          requesting client. In order to prevent DDoS (Distributed Denial of
          Service) attacks, the server SHOULD restrict the number of FAIL
          messages sent to a requesting client. It MAY also rate-limit FAIL
          messages.</t>

          <t>A flow example is shown in <xref target="decline"></xref>.</t>

          <t><figure align="center" anchor="decline"
              title="DECLINE Flow Example">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |=======QUOTATION(Requested CPD)=====>|
   |<============PROCESSING==============|
   |<=========OFFER(Offered CPD)=========|
   |=============PROCESSING=============>|
   |===============DECLINE==============>|
   |<================ACK=================|
   |                                     |
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ack" title="ACK">
          <t>The format of the ACK message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="17" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;ACK Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME&gt;]</t>

              <t>[&lt;CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;]</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This message is issued by the server to
          close a CPNP transaction or by a client to grant more negotiation
          time to the server.</t>

          <t>This message is sent by the server as a response to an ACCEPT,
          WITHDRAW, DECLINE, or CANCEL message. In this case, the ACK message
          MUST include the copy of the service description document as stored
          by the server. In particular, the following considerations are taken
          into account for connectivity provisioning services:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list
              style="symbols">
              <t>A copy of the requested/offered CPD is included by the server
              if it successfully handled a CANCEL message.</t>

              <t>A copy of the updated CPD is included by the server if it
              successfully handled an UPDATE message.</t>

              <t>A copy of the offered CPD is included by the server if it
              successfully handled an ACCEPT message in the context of a
              QUOTATION transaction (refer to "Agreed CPD" in <xref
              target="cpd"></xref>).</t>

              <t>An empty CPD is included by the server if it successfully
              handled a DECLINE or WITHDRAW message.<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>A client may issue an ACK message as a response to a time
          extension request (conveyed in PROCESSING) received from the server.
          In such case, the ACK message MUST include an EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME
          that is likely to be set to the time extension requested by the
          server.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="cancel" title="CANCEL">
          <t>The format of the CANCEL message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="21" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;CANCEL Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;]</t>
            </list><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>The client can issue a CANCEL
          message at any stage during the CPNP negotiation process before an
          agreement is reached. CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER and
          TRANSACTION_ID are used by the server as keys to find the
          corresponding order. If a quotation order matches, the server
          changes the state of this quotation order to "Cancelled" and then
          returns an ACK with a copy of the requested CPD to the requesting
          client.</t>

          <t>If no quotation order is found, the server returns a FAIL message
          to the requesting client.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="with" title="WITHDRAW">
          <t>The format of the WITHDRAW message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="23" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;WITHDRAW Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;NONCE&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;AGREED_CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;]</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This message is used to withdraw an offer
          already accepted by the Customer. <xref target="withdraw"></xref>
          shows a typical usage of this message.</t>

          <t><figure align="center" anchor="withdraw"
              title="WITHDRAW Flow Example">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |============WITHDRAW(CPD)===========>|
   |<============PROCESSING==============|
   |<===========ACK(Empty CPD)===========|
   |                                     |
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The CPNP MUST include the same CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER,
          PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, and NONCE as those used when creating
          the order.</t>

          <t>Upon receipt of a WITHDRAW message, the server checks whether an
          order matching the request is found. If an order is found, the state
          of the order is changed to "Cancelled" and an ACK message including
          an Empty CPD is returned to the requesting client. If no order is
          found, the server returns a FAIL message to the requesting
          client.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="upd" title="UPDATE">
          <t>The format of the UPDATE message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="21" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;UPDATE Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;NONCE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;REQUESTED_CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This message is sent by the CPNP client
          to update an existing service agreement (e.g., connectivity
          provisioning agreement). The CPNP MUST include the same
          CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, and
          NONCE as those used when creating the order. The CPNP client
          includes a new service description (e.g., updated CPD) which
          integrates the requested modifications. A new Transaction_ID MUST be
          assigned by the client.</t>

          <t>Upon receipt of an UPDATE message, the server checks whether an
          order, having state "Completed", matches
          CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, and
          NONCE. <?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list style="symbols">
              <t>If no order is found, the CPNP server generates a FAIL error
              with the appropriate error code (<xref
              target="fail"></xref>).</t>

              <t>If an order is found, the server checks whether it can honor
              the request:<list style="symbols">
                  <t>A FAIL message is sent to the client if the server cannot
                  honor the request. The client may initiate a new PQO
                  negotiation cycle (that is, a new UPDATE).</t>

                  <t>An OFFER message including the updated clauses (e.g.,
                  updated connectivity provisioning document) is sent to the
                  client. For example, the server maintains an order for
                  provisioning a VPN service that connects sites A, B, and C.
                  If the client sends an UPDATE message to remove site C, only
                  sites A and B will be included in the OFFER sent by the
                  server to the requesting client.<vspace
                  blankLines="1" />Note that the cycle that is triggered by an
                  UPDATE message is also considered as a negotiation
                  cycle.<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>A flow chart that illustrates the use of UPDATE operation is
          shown in <xref target="update"></xref>.<figure align="center"
              anchor="update" title="UPDATE Flow Example">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |=========UPDATE(Requested CPD)======>|
   |<============PROCESSING==============|
   |<=========OFFER(Updated CPD)=========|
   |=============PROCESSING=============>|
   |==========ACCEPT(Updated CPD)=======>|
   |<==========ACK(Updated CPD)==========|
   |                                     |
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fail" title="FAIL">
          <t>The format of the FAIL message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="19" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;FAIL Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;STATUS_CODE&gt;</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This message is sent in the following
          cases:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list style="symbols">
              <t>The server cannot honor an order received from the client
              (i.e., received in a QUOTATION or UPDATE request).</t>

              <t>The server encounters an error when processing a CPNP request
              received from the client.</t>

              <t>The client cannot grant more time to the server. This is a
              response to a time extension request carried in a PROCESSING
              message.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The status code indicates the error code. The following codes are
          supported:<list hangIndent="5" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="1 (Message Validation Error): "><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The message cannot be validated (see <xref
              target="validation"></xref>).</t>

              <t hangText="2 (Authentication Required):"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request cannot be handled because
              authentication is required.</t>

              <t hangText="3 (Authorization Failed): "><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request cannot be handled because
              authorization failed.</t>

              <t hangText="4 (Administratively prohibited): "><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request cannot be handled because of
              administrative policies.</t>

              <t hangText="5 (Out of Resources): "><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request cannot be honored because resources
              (e.g., capacity) are insufficient.</t>

              <t hangText="6 (Network Presence Error): "><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request cannot be honored because there is
              no network presence.</t>

              <t hangText="7 (More Time Rejected):"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request to extend the time for negotiation
              is rejected by the client.</t>

              <t hangText="8 (Unsupported Activation Type):"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />The request cannot be handled because the
              requested activation type is not supported.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="activate" title="ACTIVATE">
          <t>The format of the ACTIVATE message is shown below:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?></t>

          <t><list hangIndent="21" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;ACTIVATE Message&gt; ::=">&lt;VERSION&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;METHOD_CODE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;SEQUENCE_NUMBER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;TRANSACTION_ID&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;NONCE&gt;</t>

              <t>&lt;ACTIVATION_SCHEDULE&gt;</t>

              <t>[&lt;INFORMATION_ELEMENT&gt;...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This message is sent by the CPNP client
          to request the activation of an existing service agreement. The
          message MUST include the same CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER,
          PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, and NONCE as those used when creating
          the order. The CPNP client may includes a schedule target for
          activating this order. A new Transaction_ID MUST be assigned by the
          client.</t>

          <t>Upon receipt of an UPDATE message, the server checks whether an
          order, having state "Completed", matches
          CUSTOMER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER, and
          NONCE. <?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list style="symbols">
              <t>If no completed order is found, the CPNP server generates a
              FAIL error with the appropriate error code (<xref
              target="fail"></xref>).</t>

              <t>If an order is found, the server checks whether it can honor
              the request:<list style="symbols">
                  <t>A FAIL message is sent to the client if the server cannot
                  honor the request (e.g., out of resources or explicit
                  activation wasn't negotiated with this client).</t>

                  <t>An ACK is sent to the client to confirm that the
                  immediate activation (or de-activation) of the order or its
                  successful scheduling if a non-null ACTIVATION_SCHEDULE was
                  included in the request. Note that setting
                  ACTIVATION_SCHEDULE to 0 in an ACTIVATE request has a
                  special meaning: it is used to request a de-activation of an
                  agreed order. <?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>

          <t><xref target="activateex"></xref> illustrates the use of ACTIVATE
          operation.<figure align="center" anchor="activateex"
              title="ACTIVATE Flow Example">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+------+                              +------+
|Client|                              |Server|
+------+                              +------+
   |================ACTIVATE()==========>|
   |<==============ACK()=================|
   |                                     |
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="validation" title="CPNP Message Validation">
      <t>Both client and server proceed with CPNP message validation. The
      following tables summarize the validation checks to be followed.</t>

      <section title="On the Client Side">
        <t></t>

        <texttable style="headers">
          <ttcol>Operation</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Validation Checks</ttcol>

          <c>PROCESSING</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier}
          must match an existing PQO with a state set to "PQOSent". The
          sequence number carried in the packet must be larger than the
          sequence number maintained by the client.</c>

          <c>OFFER</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier}
          must match an existing order with state set to "PQOSent" or {Source
          IP address, source port number, destination IP address, destination
          port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier, Provider
          Order Identifier} must match an existing order with a state set to
          "ServerProcessing". The sequence number carried in the packet must
          be larger than the sequence number maintained by the client.</c>

          <c>ACK (QUOTATION Transaction)</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier,
          Provider Order Identifier, Offered Connectivity Provisioning Order}
          must match an order with a state set to "AcceptSent". The sequence
          number carried in the packet must be larger than the sequence number
          maintained by the client.</c>

          <c>ACK (UPDATE Transaction)</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier,
          Provider Order Identifier, Updated Connectivity Provisioning Order}
          must match an order with a state set to "AcceptSent". The sequence
          number carried in the packet must be larger than the sequence number
          maintained by the client.</c>

          <c>ACK (WITHDRAW Transaction)</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier,
          Provider Order Identifier, Empty Connectivity Provisioning Order}
          must match an order with a state set to "Cancelled". The sequence
          number carried in the packet must be larger than the sequence number
          maintained by the client.</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="On the Server Side">
        <t></t>

        <texttable style="headers">
          <ttcol>Method</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Validation Checks</ttcol>

          <c>QUOTATION</c>

          <c>The source IP address passes existing access filters (if any).
          The sequence number carried in the packet must not be lower than the
          sequence number maintained by the server.</c>

          <c>PROCESSING</c>

          <c>The sequence number carried in the packet must be greater than
          the sequence number maintained by the server.</c>

          <c>CANCEL</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier}
          must match an order with state set to "PQOReceived" or
          "OfferProposed" or "ProcessingReceived" or "AcceptReceived ". The
          sequence number carried in the packet must be greater than the
          sequence number maintained by the server.</c>

          <c>ACCEPT</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier,
          Provider Order Identifier, Nonce, Offered Connectivity Provisioning
          Order} must match an order with state set to "OfferProposed" or
          "ProcessingReceived". The sequence number carried in the packet must
          be greater than the sequence number maintained by the server.</c>

          <c>FAIL</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier,
          Provider Order Identifier} must match an order with state set to
          "AwaitingProcessing" and for which a request to grant more time to
          process an offer was requested. The sequence number carried in the
          packet must be greater than the sequence number maintained by the
          server.</c>

          <c>DECLINE</c>

          <c>{Source IP address, source port number, destination IP address,
          destination port number, Transaction-ID, Customer Order Identifier,
          Provider Order Identifier, Nonce} must match an order with state set
          to "OfferProposed" or "ProcessingReceived". The sequence number
          carried in the packet must be greater than the sequence number
          maintained by the server.</c>

          <c>UPDATE</c>

          <c>The source IP address passes existing access filters (if any) and
          {Customer Order Identifier, Provider Order Identifier, Nonce} must
          match an existing order with state "Completed".</c>

          <c>WITHDRAW</c>

          <c>The source IP address passes existing access filters (if any) and
          {Customer Order Identifier, Provider Order Identifier, Nonce} must
          match an existing order with state "Completed".</c>

          <c>ACTIVATE</c>

          <c>The source IP address passes existing access filters (if any) and
          {Customer Order Identifier, Provider Order Identifier, Nonce} must
          match an existing order with state "Completed" for which the
          activation procedure is tagged to be explicit.</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="behavior" title="Theory of Operation">
      <t>Both CPNP client and server proceed with message validation checks as
      specified in <xref target="validation"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Client Behavior">
        <t></t>

        <section anchor="creation" title="Order Negotiation Cycle">
          <t>To place a provisioning quotation order, the client first
          initiates a local quotation order object identified by a unique
          identifier assigned by the client (Client Order Identifier). The
          state of the quotation order is set to "Created". The client then
          generates a QUOTATION request which includes the assigned
          identifier, possibly an expected response time, a Transaction-ID,
          and a Requested Service (e.g., Requested Connectivity Provisioning
          Document). The client may include additional Information Elements
          such as Negotiation Options or Activation Type.</t>

          <t>The client may be configured to not enforce negotiation checks on
          EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME; if so, no EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME attribute (or
          EXPECTED_RESPONSE_TIME set to infinite) should be included in the
          quotation order.</t>

          <t>Once the request is sent to the server, the state of the request
          is set to "PQOSent" and a timer, if a response time is included in
          the quotation order, is set to the expiration time as included in
          the QUOTATION request. The client also maintains a copy of the CPNP
          session entry details used to generate the QUOTATION request. The
          CPNP client must listen on the same port number that it used to send
          the QUOTATION request.</t>

          <t>If no answer is received from the server before the
          retransmission timer expires (i.e., RETRANS_TIMER, <xref
          target="timers"></xref>), the client retransmits the message until
          maximum retry is reached (e.g., 3 times). The same sequence number
          is used for retransmitted packets.</t>

          <t>If a FAIL message is received, the client may decide to issue
          another (corrected) request towards the same server, cancel the
          local order, or contact another server. The behavior of the client
          depends on the error code returned by the server in the FAIL
          message.</t>

          <t>If a PROCESSING message matching the CPNP session entry (<xref
          target="session"></xref>) is received, the client updates the CPNP
          session entry with the PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER information. If
          the client does not accept the expected offer time that may have
          been indicated in the PROCESSING message, the client may decide to
          cancel the quotation order. If the client accepts the
          EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME, it changes the state of the order to
          "ServerProcessing" and sets a timer to the value of
          EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME. If no offer is made before the timer expires,
          the client changes the state of the order to "Cancelled".</t>

          <t>As a response to a time extension request (conveyed in a
          PROCESSING message that included a new EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME), the
          client may grant this extension by issuing an ACK message or reject
          the time extension with a FAIL message having a status code set to
          "More Time Rejected".</t>

          <t>If an OFFER message matching the CPNP session entry is received,
          the client checks if a PROCESSING message having the same
          PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER has been received from the server. If
          a PROCESSING message was already received for the same order but the
          PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER does not match the identifier included
          in the OFFER message, the client silently ignores the message. If a
          PROCESSING message having the same PROVIDER_AGREEMENT_IDENTIFIER was
          already received and matches the CPNP transaction identifier, the
          client changes the state of the order to "OfferReceived" and sets a
          timer to the value of VALIDITY_OFFER_TIME indicated in the OFFER
          message.</t>

          <t>If an offer is received from the server (i.e., as documented in
          an OFFER message), the client may accept or reject the offer. The
          client accepts the offer by generating an ACCEPT message which
          confirms that the client agrees to subscribe to the offer documented
          in the OFFER message; the state of the order is passed to
          "AcceptSent". The transaction is terminated if an ACK message is
          received from the server. If no ACK is received from the server, the
          client proceeds with the retransmission of the ACCEPT message until
          the maximum retry is reached (<xref target="retrans"></xref>).</t>

          <t>The client may also decide to reject the offer by sending a
          DECLINE message. The state of the order is set by the client to
          "Cancelled". If an offer is not acceptable by the client, the client
          may decide to contact a new server or submit another order to the
          same server. Guidelines to issue an updated order or terminate the
          negotiation are specific to the client.</t>

          <t>An order can be activated (or de-activated) using the ACTIVATE
          message or other agreed activation means (Section 3.11 of <xref
          target="RFC7297"></xref>).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="corw" title="Order Withdrawal Cycle">
          <t>A client may withdraw a completed order. This is achieved by
          issuing a WITHDRAW message. This message MUST include Customer Order
          Identifier, Provider Identifier, and Nonce returned during the order
          negotiation cycle, as specified in <xref
          target="creation"></xref>.</t>

          <t>If no ACK is received from the server, the client proceeds with
          the retransmission of the message. If no ACK is received after the
          maximum retry is exhausted, the client should log the information
          and must send an alarm to the administrator. If there is no specific
          instruction from the administrator, the client SHOULD schedule
          another Withdrawal cycle. The client MUST NOT retry this Withdrawal
          cycle more frequently than every 300 seconds and MUST NOT retry more
          frequently than every 60 seconds.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="cordu" title="Order Update Cycle">
          <t>A client may update a completed order. This is achieved by
          issuing an UPDATE message. This message MUST include Customer Order
          Identifier, Provider Order Identifier and Nonce returned during the
          order negotiation cycle specified in <xref
          target="creation"></xref>. The client MUST include in the UPDATE
          message an updated CPD with the requested changes.</t>

          <t>Subsequent messages exchange is similar to what is documented in
          <xref target="creation"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Server Behavior">
        <t></t>

        <section anchor="handling" title="Order Processing">
          <t>Upon receipt of a QUOTATION message from a client, the server
          sets a CPNP session, stores Transaction-ID and generates a Provider
          Order Identifier. Once preliminary validation checks are completed (
          <xref target="validation"></xref>), the server may return a
          PROCESSING message to inform the client that the quotation order is
          received and it is under processing; the server may include an
          expected offer time to notify the client by when an offer will be
          proposed. An order with state "AwaitingProcessing" is created by the
          server. The server runs its decision-making process to decide which
          offer it can make to honor the received order. The offer should be
          made before the expected offer time expires.</t>

          <t>If the server cannot make an offer, it sends backs a FAIL message
          with the appropriate error code.</t>

          <t>If the server requires more negotiation time, it must send a
          PROCESSING message with a new EXPECTED_OFFER_TIME. The client may
          grant this extension by issuing an ACK message or reject the time
          extension with a FAIL message having a status code set to "More Time
          Rejected". If the client doesn't grant more time, the server must
          answer before the initial expected offer time; otherwise the client
          will decline the quotation order.</t>

          <t>If the server can honor the request or it can make an offer that
          meets only some of the requirements, it creates an OFFER message.
          The server must indicate the Transaction-ID, Customer Order
          Identifier as indicated in the QUOTATION message, and the Provider
          Order Identifier generated for this order. The server must also
          include Nonce and the offered service document (e.g., offered
          Connectivity Provisioning Document). The server includes an offer
          validity time as well. Once sent to the client, the server changes
          the state of the order to "OfferProposed" and a timer set to the
          validity time is initiated.</t>

          <t>If the server determines that additional network resources from
          another network provider are needed to accommodate a quotation
          order, it will create child PQO(s) and will behave as a CPNP client
          to negotiate child PQO(s) with possible partnering providers (see
          <xref target="child"></xref>).</t>

          <t>If no PROCESSING, ACCEPT, or DECLINE message is received before
          the expiry of the RETRANS_TIMER, the server re-sends the same offer
          to the client. This procedure is repeated until maximum retry is
          reached.</t>

          <t>If an ACCEPT message is received before the offered validity time
          expires, the server proceeds with validation checks as specified in
          <xref target="validation"></xref>. The state of the corresponding
          order is passed to "AcceptReceived". The server sends back an ACK
          message to terminate the order processing cycle.</t>

          <t>If a CANCEL/DECLINE message is received, the server proceeds with
          the cancellation of the order. The state of the order is then passed
          to "Cancelled".</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="sordw" title="Order Withdrawal">
          <t>A client may withdraw a completed order by issuing a WITHDRAW
          message. Upon receipt of a WITHDRAW message, the server proceeds
          with the validation checks, as specified in <xref
          target="validation"></xref>:<list style="symbols">
              <t>If the checks fail, a FAIL message is sent back to the client
              with the appropriate error code (e.g., 1 (Message Validation
              Error), 2 (Authentication Required), or 3 (Authorization
              Failed)).</t>

              <t>If the checks succeed, the server clears the clauses of the
              Connectivity Provisioning Document, changes the state of the
              order to "Cancelled", and sends back an ACK message with an
              Empty Connectivity Provisioning Document.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="sordu" title="Order Update">
          <t>A client may update an order by issuing an UPDATE message. Upon
          receipt of an UPDATE message, the server proceeds with the
          validation checks as specified in <xref
          target="validation"></xref>:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list
              style="symbols">
              <t>If the checks fail, a FAIL message is sent back to the client
              with the appropriate error code (e.g., 1 (Message Validation
              Error), 2 (Authentication Required), 3 (Authorization Failed),
              or 6 (Network Presence Error)).</t>

              <t>The exchange of subsequent messages is similar to what is
              specified in <xref target="creation"></xref>. The server should
              generate a new Nonce value to be included in the offer made to
              the client.<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sq_nu" title="Sequence Numbers">
        <t>In each transaction, sequence numbers are used to protect the
        transaction against replay attacks. Each communicating partner of the
        transaction maintains two sequence numbers, one for incoming packets
        and one for outgoing packets. When a partner receives a message, it
        will check whether the sequence number in the message is larger than
        the incoming sequence number maintained locally. If not, the message
        will be discarded. If the message is proved to be legitimate, the
        value of the incoming sequence number maintained locally will be
        replaced by the value of the sequence number in the message. When a
        partner sends out a message, it will insert the value of the outgoing
        sequence number into the message and increase the outgoing sequence
        number maintained locally by 1.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="retrans" title="Message Re-Transmission">
        <t>If a transaction partner sends out a message and does not receive
        any expected reply before the retransmission timer expires (i.e.,
        RETRANS_TIMER), a transaction partner will try to re-transmit the
        message. The procedure is reiterated until a maximum retry is reached
        (e.g., 3 times). An exception is the last message (e.g., ACK) sent
        from the server in a transaction. After sending this message, the
        retransmission timer will be disabled since no additional feedback is
        expected.</t>

        <t>In addition, if the partner receives a retransmission of a last
        incoming packet it handled, the partner can re-send the same answer to
        the incoming packet with a limited frequency. If no answer was
        generated at the moment, the partner needs to generate a PROCESSING
        message as the answer.</t>

        <t>To optimize message retransmission, a partner could also store the
        last incoming packet and the associated answer. Note that the times of
        retransmission could be decided by the local policy and retransmission
        will not cause any change of sequence numbers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="og" title="Some Operational Guidelines">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Logging on the CPNP Server ">
        <t>The CPNP server should be configurable to log various events and
        associated information. Such information may include:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Client's IP address</t>

            <t>Any event change (e.g., new quotation order, offer sent, order
            confirm, order cancellation, order withdraw, etc.)</t>

            <t>Timestamp<?rfc subcompact="no"?></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Business Guidelines and Objectives">
        <t>The CPNP server can operate in the following modes: <list
            style="numbers">
            <t>Fully automated mode: <vspace blankLines="1" />The CPNP server
            is provisioned with a set of business guidelines and objectives
            that will be used as an input to the decision-making process. The
            CPNP server will service received orders that fall into these
            business guidelines; otherwise, requests will be escalated to an
            administrator that will formally validate/invalidate an order
            request. The set of policies to be configured to the CPNP server
            are specific to each administrative entity managing a CPNP
            server.</t>

            <t>Administrative-based mode: <vspace blankLines="1" />This mode
            assumes some or all CPNP server' operations are subject to a
            formal administrative validation. CPNP events will trigger
            appropriate validation requests that will be forwarded to the
            contact person(s) or department which is responsible for
            validating the orders. Administrative validation messages are
            relayed using another protocol (e.g., SMTP) or a dedicated
            tool.</t>
          </list>Business guidelines are local to each administrative entity.
        How validation requests are presented to an administrator are out of
        scope of this document; each administrative entity may decide the
        appropriate mechanism to enable for that purpose.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Means to defend the server against denial-of-service attacks must be
      enabled. For example, access control lists (ACLs) can be enforced on the
      client, the server or the network in between, to allow a trusted client
      to communicate with a trusted server.</t>

      <t>The client and the server MUST be mutually authenticated.
      Authenticated encryption MUST be used for data confidentiality and
      message integrity.</t>

      <t>The protocol does not provide security mechanisms to protect the
      confidentiality and integrity of the packets transported between the
      client and the server. An underlying security protocol such as (e.g.,
      Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>,
      Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8446"></xref>) MUST be
      used to protect the integrity and confidentiality of protocol messages.
      In this case, if it is possible to provide an Automated Key Management
      (AKM) and associate each transaction with a different key,
      inter-transaction replay attacks can naturally be addressed. If the
      client and the server use a single key, an additional mechanism should
      be provided to protect inter-transaction replay attacks between them.
      Clients MUST implement DTLS record replay detection (Section 3.3 of
      <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>) or an equivalent mechanism to protect
      against replay attacks.</t>

      <t>DTLS and TLS with a cipher suite offering confidentiality protection
      and the guidance given in <xref target="RFC7525"></xref> MUST be
      followed to avoid attacks on (D)TLS.</t>

      <t>The client MUST silently discard CPNP responses received from unknown
      CPNP servers. The use of a randomly generated Transaction-ID makes it
      hard to forge a response from a server with a spoofed IP address
      belonging to a legitimate CPNP server. Furthermore, CPNP demands that
      messages from the server must include the correct identifiers of the
      orders. Two order identifiers are used: one generated by the client and
      a second one generated by the server.</t>

      <t>The Provider MUST enforce means to protect privacy-related
      information included the documents (see <xref target="cpd"></xref>)
      exchanged in CPNP messages <xref target="RFC6462"></xref>. In
      particular, this information MUST NOT be revealed to external parties
      without the consent of Customers. Providers should enforce policies to
      make Customer fingerprinting difficult to achieve. For more discussion
      about privacy, refer to <xref target="RFC6462"></xref><xref
      target="RFC6973"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The Nonce and the Transaction ID attributes provide sufficient
      randomness and can effectively tolerate attacks raised by off-line
      adversaries, who do not have the capability of eavesdropping and
      intercepting the packets transported between the client and the server.
      Only authorized clients must be able to modify agreed CPNP orders. The
      use of a randomly generated Nonce by the server makes it hard to modify
      an agreement on behalf of a malicious third-party.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not request any IANA action.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Diego R. Lopez and Adrian Farrel for the comments.</t>

      <t>Thanks to the ISE reviewers.</t>

      <t>Special thanks to Luis Miguel Contreras Murillo for the detailed
      review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4086'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5511'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7525'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8446'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6347'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7297'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3339'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4176'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8309'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6241'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8259'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7149'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4026'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6973'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6462'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6770'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2782'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6574'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6793'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6830'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3084'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7049'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.boucadair-lisp-idr-ms-discovery'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.geng-netslices-architecture'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8329'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7215'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7491'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8040'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8597'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-opsawg-l3sm-l3nm'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.itsumo-dsnp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.nguyen-rap-cops-sls'?>

      <reference anchor="ETICS"
                 target="https://www.ict-etics.eu/fileadmin/documents/news/ETICS_white_paper_final.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Economics and Technologies of Inter-Carrier Services</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="">
            <organization>EU FP7 ETICS Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="January" year="2014" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AGAVE"
                 target="https://rd.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12243-009-0103-4">
        <front>
          <title>The AGAVE Approach for Network Virtualization: Differentiated
          Services Delivery</title>

          <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M."
                  surname="Boucadair">
            <organization>EU FP7 ETICS Project</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Panos Georgatsos" initials="P."
                  surname="Georgatsos">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="N. Wang" initials="N." surname="Wang">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Griffin" initials="D." surname="Griffin">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Pavlou" initials="G." surname="Pavlou">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Howarth" initials="M." surname="Howarth">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Elizondo" initials="A." surname="Elizondo">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="10" month="April" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TEQUILA"
                 target="https://www.ist-tequila.org/presentations/srnp-pipcm.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Service Negotiation Protocol (SrNP)</title>

          <author fullname="Panos Georgatsos" initials="P."
                  surname="Georgatsos">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Dimitris  Giannakopoulos" initials="G."
                  surname="Giannakopoulos">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Xin"
                 target="http://www.cs.columbia.edu/~xinwang/public/projects/protocol.html">
        <front>
          <title>Resource Negotiation and Pricing Protocol (RNAP)</title>

          <author fullname="Xin Wang" initials="X." surname="Wang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Karl"
                 target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.19.5907">
        <front>
          <title>SNAP: A Protocol for Negotiating Service Level Agreements and
          Coordinating Resource Management in Distributed Systems</title>

          <author fullname="Karl Czajkowski">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Ian Foster">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Carl Kesselman ">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Volker Sander">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Steven Tuecke">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
